Catalog of the Walt Whitman Literary Manuscripts in The Charles E. Feinberg Collection of the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1839-1919, Library of Congress, Washington, DC.
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
- Notes and Notebooks, 1847-91, undated (Box 37, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40, Box 41, Box 42)
  - [In his presence], 1850–1871; loc.00483; xxx.00264; prose poetry 14 leaves handwritten
    A notebook containing both prose and verse notes. Content from the twentieth image was revised and used in The Sleepers, which first appeared as the fourth poem under the repeated title Leaves of Grass in Leaves of Grass ( 1855 ). Whitman changed the title of this poem two more times, Night Poem ( 1856 ) and Sleep-Chasings ( 1860 ), before settling on the final title in the 1871 edition of Leaves of Grass. This poem went through further revisions until 1881. All subsequent reprintings of The Sleepers overseen by Whitman are identical to the poem as it appeared in the 1881 edition of Leaves of Grass. For more on the development of this poem, see The Changing shape of 'The Sleepers,' with special attention to the 'Lucifer' passage.
  - [16th Sept], undated; loc.00354; xxx.00047; poetry prose 46 leaves handwritten (Box 38, Folder Undated Thoughts, Ideas, and Trial lines (3 V.))
    An early notebook Whitman used for various purposes. William White, in his edition of Whitman's Daybooks and Notebooks (New York: New York University Press, 1978. 3 vols.), noted a relationship between rough drafts of poems in this notebook (called An Early Notebook in White's edition) and the poem Starting from Paumanok. Drafts of poems also appear under the titles A Poem of Maternity, Poem of Remorse, and two titled Proem (surfaces 26, 79, 81, and 86, respectively). Whitman has written upside down on several of the leaves. An image of the recto of surface 86 is unavailable.
  - [No doubt the efflux of the soul], 1856–1871; loc.00025; xxx.00111; xxx.00264; prose poetry 14 leaves handwritten (Box 38, Folder Undated Thoughts, Ideas, and Trial lines (3 V.))
    Also known as the "Sleepers Notebook," this manuscript is composed almost entirely in prose. However, the ideas developed throughout much of this notebook have been linked to the poem, The Sleepers, a version of which appeared in Leaves of Grass in 1855. Additionally, some phrases which appear in this notebook were used slightly revised in Song of the Open Road, first published in the 1856 edition of Leaves of Grass as Poem of the Road.
  - [Free cider], between 1850-1860; loc.00156; xxx.00747; poetry prose 2 leaves handwritten (Box 38, Folder Brooklyniana, Undated, Free cider and Long Island character.)
    Notes which include the first two lines of a draft of a poem beginning You fired the shot. It is written in pencil on both sides of a narrow strip of lined paper, cut from a larger sheet.
  - [from the tips of his fingers], about 1855; loc.05705; xxx.00048; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 38, Folder Notes & Nbks Brooklyniana Fulton St)
    Cancelled and fragmentary lines that were revised and used in what became section 39 of the final version of Song of Myself, a poem first published in Leaves of Grass ( 1855 ). The prose note on the other side of the leaf concerns Brooklyn history, though no connection between it and Whitman's published work on that subject has been established.
  - Western Nicknames, about 1885; loc.07052; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 39, Folder 1847-1869, words and nicknames)
    On one side of the manuscript leaf are notes about demonyms for the people of various places in North America. Whitman made use of this list in his essay Slang in America, which was first published in the November 1885 issue of The North American Review and later collected in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The other side, which has been cancelled, contains a partial draft of an article written in response to an unidentified author who had apparently found fault with American politics and newspaper literature. It is unknown whether the writing on this side led to publication. No images of this item are currently available.
  - [med Cophósis], between 1850-1856; loc.00005; xxx.00250; xxx.00221; xxx.00113; xxx.00226; poetry 2 leaves handwritten (Box 39, Folder Literary, Before 1855, Women)
    A notebook kept by Whitman in the early to mid-1850s. William White, in his edition of Whitman's Daybooks and Notebooks, 3 vols. (New York: New York University Press, 1978 ), noted a relationship between this notebook and the poems Who Learns My Lesson Complete?, By Blue Ontario's Shore, Song of the Answerer, and There Was a Child Went Forth.
  - ['wood drake'], about 1855; loc.00158; xxx.00048; poetry prose handwritten 2 leaves (Box 39, Folder Literary, Before 1855, Wood Drake)
    An early manuscript. William White, in his edition of Whitman's Daybooks and Notebooks, 3 vols. (New York: New York University Press, 1978 ), noted a relationship between material in this manuscript and the poem Song of Myself, specifically section 13, lines 237–243.
  - [rule in all addresses], undated; loc.00163; xxx.00748; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 39, Folder Literary, Rule in All Addresses.)
    A page of notes with various trial lines and ideas for poems, including "poem descriptive of a good wife," a poem beginning "What is Beauty?," and several lines of Whitmanian cataloguing.
  - [The Trapper's Bride], 1856 or later; loc.00164; xxx.00749; poetry printed handwritten 1 leaf (Box 39, Folder Literary, 1856, Indian Theme for Poem)
    A clipping of an article entitled "The Indian in American Art" from The Crayon: A Journal Devoted to the Graphic Arts, and the Literature Related to Them, with a piece of paper pasted to the bottom containing an idea for a poem about Native Americans. At the top is written "The Trapper's Bride by a Baltimore artist." A date on the verso indicates that the document is from January 1856.
  - Airs of Lilac Time, about 1870; loc.00145; xxx.00750; poetry prose handwritten 4 leaves (Box 39, Folder Literary, 1870? Airs of Lilac Time)
    A bound notebook with a title page reading "Airs of Lilac Time for 1870, '71, &c" and two pages with lists of words and a few trial lines.
  - [for 'Again old heart so gay'], 1872; loc.00619; xxx.00284; poetry prose handwritten 2 leaves (Box 39, Folder Literary, 1871, Again Old Heart.)
    Two pages of notes for a piece entitled Again old heart so gay about "the idea of constantly recurring Birth and Death." This manuscript is probably related to By Broad Potomac's Shore, first published in 1872.
  - The Poetry of the War at last, about 1880; loc.00165; xxx.01010; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 39, Folder c. 1880, Poetry of the War At Last)
    A draft of a prose piece entitled The Poetry of the War at last. It doesn't appear that such a piece was ever published.
  - [Philadelphia, Pa], about 1880-81; loc.00166; xxx.00751; poetry prose handwritten 7 leaves (Box 39, Folder c. 1880-81, Comrades.)
    A small notebook held together by a pin with notes and trial lines for a poem about comrades.
  - [Make a piece], about 1890; loc.03408; xxx.00559; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 39, Folder Judgments of People)
    Notes about historical examples of extreme reactions against seemingly unobjectionable works and practices. Whitman used these ideas in Old Poets, which was first published in 1888 in November Boughs and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [more books], about 1885; loc.03403; xxx.00966; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 39, Folder 18)
    Manuscript draft fragment for an article that appeared under the title Walt Whitman at Camden in the February 28, 1885 issue of the Critic under the pseudonym George Selwyn. The article was the seventh in the magazine's Authors at Home series.
  - for Mulleins & BB, between 1873 and 1882; loc.03401; xxx.00819; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 39, Folder 18)
    On one side of this scrap are notes about the tulip tree (Liriodendron), which Whitman used in The Lesson of a Tree, first published in Specimen Days & Collect in 1882–1883. It was later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The other side of the scrap bears a quotation from John Addington Symonds's Studies of the Greek Poets, the first edition of which was published in 1873.
  - [Between this beautiful], undated; loc.00162; xxx.00113; poetry prose handwritten 6 leaves (Box 40, Folder Literary, Undated, The Voice of Walt Whitman.)
    A draft of a poem likely relating to Song of the Answerer collected in a bound book of Whitman manuscripts under the general title Walt Whitman: A Series of Six Pieces, Original Holograph Manuscripts. Drafts of prose appear on the other leaves, including a draft resembling the beginning of The Eighteenth Presidency!
  - [such things], undated; loc.00167; xxx.00753; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 40, Folder Literary, Undated, Model American)
    One leaf, heavily revised, with prose notes about the mental and moral consciousness of states.
  - [reject the claims of the genre Culturists], undated; loc.02307; xxx.00754; prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 40, Folder Literary, Undated, Model American)
    One leaf with notes about how American life and character differs from the "claims of the culturists."
  - [Draw a picture of a model], about 1868; loc.02308; xxx.00755; xxx.00967; xxx.00524; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 40, Folder Literary, Undated, Model American)
    The description of "a model American young man" inscribed on this manuscript likely contributes to Whitman's journalism of the late 1850s and represents an early stage of the "model or portrait of Personality, for general use, for the manliness of The States" that Whitman set forth in his essay Personalism, which appeared in the May 1868 issue of The Galaxy. He later combined the material from this and other essays to form Democratic Vistas, published as a monograph in 1871 and reprinted in Two Rivulets ( 1876 ), Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ), Democratic Vistas, and Other Papers ( 1888 ), and Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [in the west], undated; loc.00168; xxx.00756; prose poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 40, Folder Literary, Undated, Poem of the Vision of the West)
    Notes for a poem offering a vision of the American west centuries in the future.
  - [Railroad poem], undated; loc.00147; xxx.00757; poetry prose handwritten 1 leaf (Box 40, Folder Literary, Undated, Railroad Poem)
    Notes for several ideas for poems, including the railroad, mines, "corn and meat," and "the Man's hand and the Woman's hand." At the bottom is a longer prose note describing Whitman's goals for a large work about the American West.
  - Rel., undated; loc.00170; xxx.00758; poetry handwritten 2 leaves (Box 40, Folder Literary, Undated, Religion)
    Two leaves of notes entitled Rel. and discussing issues related to religion. A note in another hand in the top margin declares that the note is from before the Civil War.
  - [dear to me], undated; loc.00171; xxx.00759; poetry handwritten 2 leaves (Box 40, Folder Literary, Undated, The States and Their Resources)
    a draft line of poetry describing the land that is "dear" to the poet. Whitman had "Always the South" in mind as he composed the line, though this phrase was deleted.
  - Cluster of Sonnet Poems, undated; loc.00172; xxx.00760; poetry prose handwritten 2 leaves (Box 40, Folder Literary, Undated, These Days)
    Notes for a "Cluster of Sonnet Poems" about the "splendor and copiousness of These Days."
  - [The Voice], undated; loc.00173; xxx.00761; poetry handwritten 1 leaf (Box 40, Folder Literary, Undated, The Voice)
    Notes for a poem about the voices inside the heads of Socrates and Joan of Arc.
  - Poem of the Trainer, about 1860; loc.06005; xxx.00115; xxx.00128; xxx.00614; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 40, Folder The voice of Walt Whitman)
    One leaf made by pasting together two scraps of pink paper, probably wrappers from the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. On one side of the leaf are approximately four lines, written and revised in ink, about the 1833 Leonid meteor shower. These lines may be related to the poem Year of Meteors. (1859–1860), first published in Drum-Taps ( 1865 ). Richard Maurice Bucke's transcription of these lines in Notes and Fragments ( 1899 ) begins with another version of these lines and an additional line following them. It is possible that these lines were present on the manuscript when he made his transcription but have since been cut off, though it is also possible that Bucke combined transcriptions from separate leaves. The now-absent final line of Bucke's transcription reads, "Such have I in the round house hanging—such pictures name I—and they are but little." If indeed Whitman wrote this line as part of the present manuscript, it would connect it with the early poem Pictures, unpublished during Whitman's lifetime. On the reverse are the trial title Poem of the Trainer, which is written in ink, and several fragmentary lines written in pencil, describing a whale hunt. The first of these is not known to have any relationship to Whitman's published works. The pencilled lines are probably related to lines on the same topic in A Song of Joys, first published as Poem of Joys in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass.
  - earliest spring wildflowers, about 1881; loc.03419; xxx.00955; prose 1 leaf handwritten printed (Box 40, Folder 66)
    Newspaper clipping and notes regarding wildflowers that bloom in early spring. This item was likely created in conjunction with Whitman's composition of Days at J. B.'s—Turf Fires—Spring Songs, which was first published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882–1883 ). It was also later printed in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - [(Major) Col. Clifton K. Prentiss], 1865–1875; loc.01784; xxx.00502; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 41, Folder Personal, Aug 20 1865, Death of Clifton K. Prentiss)
    Notes on the Death of Clifton K. Prentiss, which were revised and appeared in Memoranda During the War ( 1875–1876 ) before being collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
  - Antietam, Manassas, 1870–1880; loc.01780; xxx.00976; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 41, Folder Undated, War Notes)
    A list of Civil War battles that includes a draft of a poetic line with no known connection to Whitman's published work.
  - [The long], 1861–1876; loc.01779; xxx.00970; poetry 1 leaf handwritten (Box 41, Folder Undated, War Notes)
    Draft lines toward an unpublished poem on the "measureless history" of the trenches.
  - Walt Whitman's Book, 1888; loc.00344; xxx.00460; prose prose leaves handwritten printed (Box 41, Folder Miscellany, Undated, Walt Whitman's books)
    A collection of papers, some of which are print proofs with handwritten comments, some of which are small scraps of handwriting, relating to both poetry and prose from November Boughs ( 1888 ).
  - [answer the point], about 1867; loc.03681; xxx.00944; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    This short note provides phrases that contributed to the essay Democracy, which was published in the December 1867 issue of The Galaxy. When Whitman combined this and two other essays to form the pamphlet-length essay Democratic Vistas ( 1871 ), he ommitted the section containing the phrases in this manuscript.
  - Brooklyn theatres, about 1862; loc.04742; xxx.00945; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Two paragraphs, lightly corrected, about the first theater building in Brooklyn. Whitman used this material in the eighth installment of Brooklyniana; A Series of Local Articles, on Past and Present. This series was published in the Brooklyn Standard between June 3, 1861 and November 1, 1862. Brooklyniana, No. 13 appeared on January 25, 1862.
  - In writing my history of Brooklyn, about 1862; loc.04741; xxx.00946; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Brief note regarding some general aspects of style that Whitman intended to employ in Brooklyniana; A Series of Local Articles, on Past and Present, which was published in the Brooklyn Standard between June 3, 1861 and November 1, 1862.
  - [Brooklyn is ° latitude], about 1862; loc.04740; xxx.00947; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Whitman probably wrote these notes about Long Island's geographical dimensions and aboriginal name in the course of preparing material for Brooklyniana; A Series of Local Articles, on Past and Present, which was published in the Brooklyn Standard between June 3, 1861 and November 1, 1862. Some of the information and phrases contained in this manuscript were included in the thirteenth installment, which appeared on March 1, 1862.
  - [Man's physiology complete I sing.], about 1867; loc.04672; xxx.00024; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten
    This manuscript fragment, written in ink and heavily corrected in pencil, contributed to the poem that appeared on the frontispiece of the 1867 edition of Leaves of Grass under the title Inscription. A revised and final version appeared in the 1871-72 edition, as the first poem of the Inscriptions cluster, with the title One's-Self I Sing.
  - [To-day completes my three-score-and], 1889; loc.04657; xxx.00948; prose poetry 1 leaf printed handwritten
    Printer's copy of the Prefatory Letter to the Reader that appeared in the 1889 printing of Leaves of Grass as an introduction to the essay A Backward Glance O'er Travel'd Roads. This letter was omitted in the so-called "deathbed edition" of 1891–92.
  - [*current aims], about 1890; loc.04536; xxx.00558; prose 3 leaves handwritten (Box 39, Folder Literary, Undated, Cosmic Poem)
    Three manuscript fragments that contributed to An Old Man's Rejoinder, which was first published in the August 16, 1890 issue of the Critic and later reprinted in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ) and Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). On the reverse of the second manuscript leaf is the end of a letter from Otto L. Levy.
  - [Somewhere I have found Carlyle announcing], about 1890; loc.04413; xxx.00558; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Manuscript notes, heavily revised, apparently for the preface to Whitman's 1891 volume Good-Bye My Fancy, although the printed preface (titled Preface Note to 2d Annex, Concluding L. of G.—1891) incorporates very few of the actual words and phrases from this manuscript. The preface was later reprinted, without change, in the 1891-92 printing of Leaves of Grass. On the reverse is a letter from Louisa Drewry, dated July 10, 1890.
  - Memoranda, about 1883; loc.04433; xxx.00949; prose 3 leaves handwritten
    Three-page draft of The Attempted Official Suppression, a section of Part 2, Chapter 1, History of Leaves of Grass, in Richard Maurice Bucke's 1883 biography, Walt Whitman.
  - Hicks (1748–1830), about 1888; loc.03677; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten
    Notes on the life dates of various famous figures. Whitman used this information for Notes (such as they are) founded on Elias Hicks, an essay that was first published in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and later reprinted in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ). The fragmentary names at the top of the list are those of Thomas Jefferson and Johann Heinrich Pestalozzi. Whitman planned to write an essay about Elias Hicks for many years. While finishing preparations for the printing of November Boughs, Whitman told Horace Traubel, "Some of these bits were written as many as thirty years ago. Some of them I have written within the past year. They are a miscellaneous lot but they all belong in the same stream." (See Traubel, With Walt Whitman in Camden, 2: 42.) The present manuscript is stored together with many other manuscripts on the topics of Elias Hicks and Quakerism. Those that directly contributed to the published essay are described separately. Those whose relationship to the published essay are unclear are not included at this stage of our work.
  - Occasional Pieces of Poetry, about 1887–1888; loc.03449; xxx.00761; xxx.00371; xxx.00372; xxx.00352; poetry prose about 13 printed and handwritten
    Whitman's copy of John G. C. Brainard's Occasional Pieces of Poetry ( 1825 ), many pages of which bear the poet's handwriting. Whitman appears to have used the volume as a notebook of sorts, for while some of the writing seems to be related to Brainard's text most of it does not. Among the handwritten notes are several sets of ideas for poems that were never published and phrases that also appear in Whitman's personal correspondence. Some of these are phrases that Whitman inscribed in the copy of Complete Poems & Prose ( 1888 ) that he gave to Horace Traubel. On other pages are words from his letter to Anne Gilchrist of November 11, 1871. These were perhaps copied into the Brainard volume as he worked to write a poem in Gilchrist's honor, though they did not make it into Going Somewhere, the poetic tribute that Whitman published in the November 1887 issue of Lippincott's Magazine (without individual title, but in a group of four poems collectively labelled November Boughs). A draft of Going Somewhere appears elsewhere in this volume. Also present is a draft of The Dismantled Ship, which was first published in the New York Herald on February 23, 1888. Both poems were later included in November Boughs ( 1888 ) and in subsequent printings of Leaves of Grass. Only those pages with Whitman's handwritten notes are linked from this record. For a more complete discussion of this item, see Nicole Gray, Walt Whitman's Marginalia as Occasional Practice, The Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America 107 ( December 2013 ), 467–494.
- Miscellany, 1834–1918
  - A Sermon Preached in the Central Reformed Protestant Dutch Church, Brooklyn, on Sabbath Morning, the 27th Day of July, 1851, 1851 and about 1862; loc.03784; xxx.00950; prose handwritten printed (Box 48, Folder 13)
    Whitman's copy of this booklet, published in 1851, with handwritten annotations on several pages. The longest of these notes, which appears on p. 2 of the appendix, constitutes a draft of a passage that Whitman incorporated into the ninth number of his Brooklyniana series, which was published in the Brooklyn Standard on February 1, 1862. Only those pages bearing Whitman's annotations are currently linked from this record.
- Supplementary File, 1806–1981, undated
  - [a thoughtful German reader], 1881; loc.00509; xxx.00912; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box 58, Folder Leaves of Grass, 1885 edition, Manuscript page)
    This manuscript contains notes on Leaves of Grass that appeared slightly revised in an unsigned collaborative review written jointly by Sylvester Baxter and Whitman, published in the 30 October 1881 issue of the Boston Sunday Herald under the title, 'Leaves of Grass.' The Complete Poems of Walt Whitman As Published by a Famous Boston House. A Friendly Characterization of the Poet's Work.
- Oversize, 1844–1952
  - Note at Beginning, 1888; loc.02147; xxx.00968; xxx.00934; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box OV1, Folder container 19)
    Manuscript of Note at Beginning, which appeared between the title page and the table of contents of Whitman's Complete Poems & Prose in 1888. On the other side of the sheet is a deleted manuscript section from the same volume's Note at End of Complete Poems and Prose. Neither of the pieces was reprinted during Whitman's lifetime.
  - To Printer, 1888; loc.02147; xxx.00934; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box OV1, Folder container 19)
    Manuscript of Note at end of Complete Poems and Prose, published in Complete Poems & Prose ( 1888 ) and not reprinted during Whitman's lifetime.
  - consent of all the other sects, about 1888; loc.06038; xxx.00486; prose 1 leaf handwritten (Box OV 11, Folder 1888, "Elias Hicks")